"Can Stress Cause Halitosis
(Bad Breath)?"
According to the American
Dental Association,
about 50% of American adults
suffer from oral malodor,
with prevalence rates around the world
ranging from 2% to nearly 80%.
On average, it seems to be about
one in three of us on the planet Earth
have bad breath. What effect might
stress have on the smell of our breath?
Stressed students were found
to have significantly higher levels
of the "rotten egg" gas,
hydrogen sulfide,
which is one of the main volatile sulfur
compounds related to bad breath,
originating from the degradation of the
sulfur-containing amino acid cysteine,
found concentrated in animal
proteins like meat and dairy.
Were they eating different diets
or just too busy to brush?
The simplest explanation
is just the dry mouth you get
when you're super-stressed,
part of our fight or flight response.
It's the same reason
we get morning breath,
because we have decreased
saliva production when we sleep
that would otherwise
self-clean the mouth,
keeping it from becoming
like a stagnant pond.
Though maybe stress hormones
are having an effect as well.
We suspect sex hormones may play
a role, since though men and women
have the same before-and-after
rise in bad breath compounds
after a stressful situation,
women seem to start out
with higher baseline levels.
Gender appears to play
an important role.
Women have significantly worse
morning breath, for example,
and bad breath is affected
by the menstrual cycle.
In fact, that's listed as one of the
causes: so-called menstrual breath.
As you can see, there are higher
levels of bad breath compounds
in the mouths of women in the
premenstrual and menstrual phases
compared not just to men,
but the follicular phase
of their own cycle,
meaning like the first half
before ovulation.
Hmm, so maybe bad breath is a hormonal
thing more than just a dry mouth thing.
But salivary flow is also lower in
menstrual and premenstrual phases.
Check it out: significantly
less salivary flow
during menstrual flow
and right before.
So, is this all just about having
a drier mouth during stress
and certain times of the month?
How could you tease out the effects?
Well, what about studying
stressful periods.
PMS, premenstrual syndrome,
is a stressful state characterized
by irritability, tension, mood swings.
Is the menstrual dry mouth and
bad breath just due to period stress?
Apparently so. If you split women up
into those who experience PMS and
those who don't, it's only those
with PMS who suffer the rise
in bad breath compounds
as their period arrives.
But the salivary flow was
not statistically different.
So the results suggest that
a stressful situation can be
a predisposing factor for bad breath
that may have nothing to do
with dry mouth or salivary flow.
So what's going on?
It's the effects of the stress
hormones themselves
on the production of
bad breath compounds.
They dripped some stress
hormones on bad breath bacteria---
hormones like adrenaline
and cortisol---
and they started churning out
more hydrogen sulfide.
What can we do about it
if we can't treat the cause
and reduce the stress?
I have videos on dietary
changes that can help
as well as tongue cleaning methods.
And I have videos in the works
on the effects of gum chewing
and the best mouthwash to use
that doesn't kill the good
bacteria in your mouth.
Stay tuned.